Tammy Rae Carland Riot Grrrl Zine Collection 1988-2002 MSS.320
Fales Library and Special Collections
Tammy Rae Carland Riot Grrrl Zine Collection
1988-2002
Fales Library and Special Collections
Carland, Tammy Rae, 1965-
MSS.320
5.5 Linear Feet (11 manuscript boxes)
Tammy Rae Carland is a Professor at the California College of the Arts where she also chairs the Photography Program. In the 1990's Carland produced a series of fanzines, including I (heart) Amy Carter and Thorn. From 1997-2005 she co-ran Mr. Lady Records and Videos, an independent record label and video art distribution company that was dedicated to the production and distribution of queer and feminist culture. The collection contains zines from Carland's personal collection, spanning through feminist, queer, punk, and popular culture in the 1990's, beginning in 1988 through to 2002.
Provenance
The Tammy Rae Carland Riot Grrrl Zine Collection was donated by Carland to NYU Libraries in 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Related Materials
Tammy Rae Carland "I (heart) Amy Carter" Riot Grrrl Collection (MSS.290)
Kelly Marie Martin Riot Grrrl Zine Collection (MSS.349)
Mr. Lady Archive (MSS.362)
Outpunk Archive (MSS.297)
Arrangement
Zines are arranged alphabetically by zine title, under a single series.
Biographical Note
Tammy Rae Carland was born in Portland, Maine in 1965. She received her BA from The Evergreen State College, an MFA from UC Irvine, and attended the Whitney Independent Study Program. She is a Professor at the California College of the Arts, where she also chairs the Photography Program. Carland is represented by Silverman Gallery in San Francisco, and primarily works with photography, experimental video and small run publications. Her photographs have been published in several books, including The Passionate Camera; Queer Bodies of Desire, and Lesbian Art in America. Carland's fanzine writing has been republished in A Girl's Guide to Taking Over the World. She has also published photographs and received reviews of her work in numerous national media.
In the 1990's Carland produced a series of fanzines, including I (heart) Amy Carter and Thorn. She collaborated on the record art for bands Bikini Kill, The Fakes and The Butchies. From 1997-2005 she co-ran Mr. Lady Records and Videos, an independent record label and video art distribution company that was dedicated to the production and distribution of queer and feminist culture.
Scope and Content
Tammy Rae Carland Riot Grrrl Zine Collection holds Carland's personal collection of zines. Spanning from the years 1988-2002 and highly concentatred in the 1990's, the bulk of the collection covers women's and queer issues and topics, but also covers music, popular culture, social commentary, fanzines about fanzines, vegetarian/veganism, sexuality, AIDS, comics, erotica, poetry, literature, and diary-style personal musings, among others.
Punk culture.; Gender identity -- United States; Zines; Feminism; Riot grrrl movement.; Wolfe, Allison; Vail, Tobi; Neuman, Molly; Dresch, Donna
- Series I: Zines
  - 3, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Adventures of Big Girl, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ah Lost Taco, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alarm Clock, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annzine, Undated, 1996, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Antabuse, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aunt Franne, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Baa!:I'm a Sheep, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baby Sue, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bad Attitude, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bamboo Girl, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Battle Dress, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Beehive, Undated, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ben is Dead, 1992, 1993,1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bi Girl World, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bitch, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bite Size, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Blondie Fanzine, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Blunderbuss, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Body Memories, 1991, 1992, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Boji For the Mentally Ill, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Boysville U.S.A, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Brat Attack, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brow Beat, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bruce on a Stick, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bust, 1993, 1994, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bye Bye Ohio, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Campfire, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Camp Runamuck, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cartoon Self-Portrait, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Catch That Beat!, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Centerfold, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Chainsaw, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Check the Funky Contents, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chica Loca Ain't No Porcupine, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chickfactor, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chop Suey Spex, Undated, 1997, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Conyers, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Crash, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Crash Pad, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cunt, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cup Size, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cupcake Chronicles, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Curse, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dangerfox 5, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dead Jackie Susann Quarterly, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Demolition Derby, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Design No. 816, [1996] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Don't Shoot It's Only Comics, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Doris, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Dork Dyke, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Double Bill, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Drum Core, [1993] (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Elegansko, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Error-Vermiform Records, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Everybody Sucks But Me, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Evil Impulse, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Exile, [1996] (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Factsheet 5, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Fantastic Fanzine, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Fembot, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Feminist Baseball, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Femme Flik, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Femme Flicke, Undated, [1996], [1997] (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Flicker, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Frighten the Horses, 1992, 1993, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Frump, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Fuckability: 0, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fuh Cole, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Gae Raj, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Gay Hotel, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Geekgirl, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - A Girl and Her Bike, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Girl Fiend, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Scope and Content
    Issue five of Hampshire College student Christina's personal riot grrrl zine covers feelings isolation and exclusion as a queer individual. Writings cover beauty and conflicting feelings about self-presentation, frustration with punk posturing and clique attitudes instead of authenticity, ways of experiencing music that contrast with general social practice, and disillusionment with college education. She also writes about her annoyance with being perceived as exclusive, personal image and its meaning in society, making music according to the DIY ethos, female independence from the male power structure, and irritation with people who are self-righteous. The zine concludes reflections on writing and conflicting desires to maintain privacy while maintaining self-expression.
  - Girl Frenzy, [1991,1992] (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Girl Germs, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Girl Jock, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Girl on the Verge, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Girlie Jones, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Girlhero, 1993, 1994, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Girlwonder, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - GNP, Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Go Teen Go, Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Grapeline, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Gynephobia, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Harp, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Hemlock, Undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Hex, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Hippie Dick, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hissy Fitt, Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - A History in Hands, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Hmph, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Holy Titclamps, 1992, 1994, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Homoboy, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Homocore, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Homogirl, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - How I Learned To Do It Bloody Murder, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Hurricane Girl, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - I (Heart) Amy Carter, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - I (Heart) Me, Undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - I Hate Brenda Newsletter, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - I Was a Teenage Girl Army, Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - I'm So Fucking Beautiful, Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Infected Faggot Perspectives, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Inside Out, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - IQ, [1993] (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - It Grosses Her Out, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - It's Time To End the Gay Rights Movement As We Know It, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - I've Given You Nothing but Trouble, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Jigsaw, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Joezine, Undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - June Bug, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Kill Rock Stars Newsletter, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Kittums, Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Kitty Magik, 1998, 1999, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - The Ladies Art Revival, 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Ladyfest 2000 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Ladyfest Guide to Art Shows, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Lawrence the Swine, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Leaving the Family Tree, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Lesbian Connection, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Lesbotown, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Light and Shadow, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Lil' Hustler, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Lizzie, Undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Los Mylxine, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - MadWoman, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Mafouka, Undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Maximum Rock N Roll, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Menstruation Idealists, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Mi Corazon, [1998] (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Milky, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Mine: An Anthology, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Mix, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Mixzine 96, [1996] (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - MMM..., 1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mom, [1993] (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Monstar, Undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mousie, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Movement, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mucho Coolan, Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Mudflap, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - My Jodie Book, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8a)
  - My Life and My Sex Thrive In the J. Crew Catalogue, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - The Nerdy Grrrl Revolution, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Nightmare Girl, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - No Romance!, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - November, Undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Oh Boy, Undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - On Our Backs, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - The Opposite, Undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Out Against the Right, Undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Outpunk, Undated, 1995, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Outpunk/Fembot [Double Issue], Undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Outweek, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - The Pac Man Fever, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Paintspot, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Pandora's Box, [1997] (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Panophobia, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Paper Suitcase, [1998] (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Paper Tiger Television Inc, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Party, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Periphery, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Pink Identity, Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Pirate Jenny, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Planet Drag King, Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Planet Girl, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Plunger, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Poemfishgrrl, Undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Positive Living, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Portland, Undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Post, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Potluck, Undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Prick/Cunt [Double Issue], Undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Princess, 1995-1998 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Pris, Undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Prisoner: The Wentworth Star, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Psychobitch, Undated, 1994, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Purge, Undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Purple Monster On Wheels, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Pussy Boy, Undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Queer Rage!, Undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Queer Zine Explosion, 1993, 1995, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Quim, 1991, 1992, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Qvimby's Qveer Store, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Rabies: A True Story, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Rant and Rave, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Report From The Star Wars Generation, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ring of Fire, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Riot Gear, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Riot Grrrl, Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - A River Runs Through It, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Rocketdyke, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Room 112, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Ruckus, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Ruth, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Sally Tomato, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Scream Box, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Secret Agent Girl No. 666, 1997, Undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Self Absorbed, Undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Semibold, Undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Sex Variants, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Sheila-Na-Gig, Undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Siren, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Sisterhood and Struggle, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Sister Strikes, Undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Skimpy Faithy, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Skinny Tires and All..., Undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Sleater-Kinney Press, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Small Victory, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Smell of Dead Fish, Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Smite, 1994, [1994] (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Smut Peddler, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Snappy Dialogue, Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Sola Mente, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Someone Might Tell Her She Was Crazy, Undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Sonic Black Hole, Undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Space Girls, Undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Spinster, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Starbelly Via Satellite, Undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Stomping on Their Lies (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Strap Yerself In, Undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - A Student's Guide to Protesting, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Suck Don't Blow, Undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Summer of My Punk Rock, Undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Superette 13, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Swerve, 1992, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Teen Fag, 1994, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Teen Mom, Undated, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Teenage Whore Book, Undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Test Subjects, Undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - There Are Mountians..., Undated (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - This is About Suicide, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Three Dollar Bill, 1991, [1991] (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Thunderpussy, 1997, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Tobi's Veil, Undated (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Totally Fucked, Undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Tough Love, 1999, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - TPMF, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - The Trouble With Normal, [2000] (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Unauthorized Biography of Timo Ellis, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Ungrateful, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Untitled, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Up, 1999, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Utopia Roaming, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Vagabond, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Vent, Undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Venus Infers, Undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Virago, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - A Void, Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - The Volcano, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Way Down Low, 1997, 1999, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Who is This Old Fart, Anyway?, Undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Whorezine, Undated, [1993] (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Wilson Wants A Doll, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Winter Garden, Undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Womondykegirl, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Word, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Y is for Yuck, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Yo!, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - You Ain't Punk, Undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Your Head on a Platter, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Zero Hour, Undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Zine Guide, 1999 (Box 11, Folder 26)